Okay, גוט מועד. Gut Moed. Today's דף daf is סוטה י"ב. Sotah
Yud Bet. We pick up six lines from the bottom, seven lines
from the bottom, we're in the middle of אגדתא Agadata about the
slavery and of in Egypt, very appropriate for חול המועד פסח Chol
HaMoed Pesach in the context of מדה כנגד מדה, Midah Keneged Midah,
measure for measure in the משנה Mishnah by סוטה, Sotah, how that
was how what was done to the סוטה, Sotah, and also God
metes out measure for measure. So we pick up now seven lines
from the bottom י"א עמוד ב'. Yud Aleph Amud Bet. ויהי כי
יראו המילדת את האלהים ויעש להם בתים. Vayehi Ki Yaru HaMeyaldot Et
HaElohim Vaya'as Lahem Batim. When the midwives identified with יוכבד Yocheved and
מרים, Miriam, they feared God, God made for them houses. What are
these houses? רב Rav and שמואל. Shmuel. Dispute of רב Rav and
שמואל. Shmuel. חד אמר בתי כהונה ולויה. Chad Amar Batei Kehunah VeLeviyah.
One says it's houses of כהונה Kehunah and לויה, Leviyah, comes from
יוכבד, Yocheved, mother of אהרן Aaron and משה. Moshe. וחד אמר בתי
מלכות, VeChad Amar Batei Malchut, houses of kingship. We'll see have to
see about that. מאן דאמר בתי כהונה ולויה, Man DeAmar Batei Kehunah
VeLeviyah, אהרן Aaron and משה, Moshe, that's אהרן Aaron and משה, Moshe,
who really came from יוכבד, Yocheved, not מרים. Miriam. Actually they're more
לוים Leviyim of course than משה, Moshe, but he is probably the...
he is like the chief לוי Levi and אהרן Aaron is the
head of the כהונה. Kehunah. So that's בתי כהונה ולויה. Batei Kehunah
VeLeviyah. ומאן דאמר בתי מלכות, UMan DeAmar Batei Malchut, how do you
get the idea of kingship coming from יוכבד Yocheved and מרים? Miriam?
דוד נמי ממרים קאתי. David Nami MiMiriam Ka'ati. Actually דוד David is
a descendant of מרים. Miriam. Now דוד David has to come from
the tribe of יהודה, Yehudah, so how are we going to make
this work? דכתיב ותמת עזובה. DeChtiv Vatamot Azuvah. עזובה Azuvah died. And
this is in a פסוק pasuk that says that כלב Calev married
a woman by the name of עזובה. Azuvah. So כלב Calev would
be identified with כלב בן יפנה Calev Ben Yefuneh and עזובה Azuvah
would be who is from the tribe of יהודה Yehudah and עזובה
Azuvah would be identified with מרים. Miriam. So מרים Miriam died, ויקח
לו כלב את אפרת. Vayikach Lo Calev Et Efrat. He took אפרת.
Efrat. ותלד לו את חור. Vatelled Lo Et Chur. Gave birth to
חור. Chur. וכתיב VeChtiv and it says by דוד, David, ודוד בן
איש אפרתי. VeDavid Ben Ish Efrati. דוד David was the son of
an Ephrathite man, understanding that that's linking back to כלב Calev who
married a woman by the name of אפרת. Efrat. דוד David descended
from כלב Calev and therefore דוד David descended from מרים. Miriam. Now
of course the problem is it says that עזובה Azuvah which is
going to be מרים Miriam died, and אפרת Efrat was a different
wife. But as we will see, עזובה Azuvah will not only be
identified with מרים, Miriam, they'll say that she got that name because
she was abandoned and she was sickly, and then when she healed
and got better, then she became like a new wife. So מרים
Miriam is both identified with עזובה Azuvah and אפרת. Efrat. And that's
how she is ultimately the progenitor of דוד המלך. David HaMelech. Okay
so now we're going to look at the פסוקים psukim that give
us this context that כלב Calev married מרים. Miriam. וכלב בן חצרון
הוליד את עזובה אשה ואת יריעות. VeCalev Ben Chetzron Holid Et Azuvah
Isha VeEt Yeriyot. So here's where he married עזובה, Azuvah, כלב בן
חצרון Calev Ben Chetzron married עזובה Azuvah and the wife and יריעות.
Yeriyot. So this is actually a little bit complicated because what does
it mean he married... it says הוליד, Holid, he gave birth. So
if you look at the English translation they will often have gave
birth with עזובה. Azuvah. את Et meaning with, not gave birth to.
But let's see what the גמרא Gemara does. ואלה בניה, VeEleh Baneha,
these are the names of her sons, עזובה's Azuvah sons, ישר ושובב
וארדון. Yesher Shovav VeArdon.
Okay now we're going to interpret the פסוק. pasuk. בן חצרון. Ben
Chetzron. So first we have to identify this כלב Calev with כלב
בן יפנה. Calev Ben Yefuneh. So what do you mean בן חצרון?
Ben Chetzron? בן יפנה הוא. Ben Yefuneh Hu. He's כלב בן יפנה.
Calev Ben Yefuneh. No, so it says בן יפנה Ben Yefuneh is
descriptive, it's not his proper name. בן שפינה מעצת מרגלים. Ben ShePinah
MeAtzat Meraglim. He turned himself away from the from the plot of
the מרגלים, Meraglim, but it is the same כלב Calev and חצרון
Chetzron is his father's literal... proper name. ואתי בן קנז הוא. VeAti
Ben Kenaz Hu. Okay one minute we've got another problem though because
כלב Calev is קניזי, Kenazi, he's identified with קנז, Kenaz, so and
not with חצרון. Chetzron. דכתיב וילכדה עתניאל בן קנז אחי כלב. DeChtiv
Vayilchedah Osniel Ben Kenaz Achi Calev. עתניאל Osniel the son of קנז
Kenaz the brother of כלב Calev conquered it. So if he's the
brother of כלב Calev and his father is קנז, Kenaz, קנז Kenaz
is also כלב's Calev father. אמר רבא חורגו דקנז הוה. Amar Rava
Chorgo DeKenaz Hava. No, no, no, he was קנז's Kenaz stepson, not
his literal son, his stepson. דייקא נמי דכתיב הקניזי. DeIka Nami DeChtiv
HaKenizi. And that's why כלב Calev is referred to as the קניזי
Kenazite and not the son of קנז, Kenaz, because he was raised
in the family of this קנז Kenaz but not his biological son.
שמע מינה. Shema Mina. Okay so that's how all of these are
the same person and that's כלב Calev in the פסוק pasuk of
בן חצרון. Ben Chetzron. Now he married this woman עזובה. Azuvah. זו
מרים. Zo Miriam. This is מרים. Miriam. ולמה נקרא שמה עזובה? VeLama
Nikra Shemah Azuvah? Why is she called עזובה? Azuvah? שכל עזבוה מתחלתה.
SheKol Azvuha MiTchilatah. Everybody abandoned her, she was a sickly child and
nobody wanted to marry her.
והוליד, VeHolid, so he gave birth to עזובה. Azuvah. What does it
mean והוליד VeHolid in the context it's clear it means he married.
והלא מנסב הוה נסיב לה. VeHalo Minsav Hava Nasiv Lah. He married
her. אמר רבי יוחנן כל הנושא אשה לשם שמים מעלה עליו הכתוב
כאילו ילדה. Amar Rabbi Yochanan Kol HaNose Isha LeShem Shamayim Ma'aleh Alav
HaKatuv KeIlu Yeladah. Any man, it means any man, who marries a
woman לשם שמים LeShem Shamayim for the sake of heaven and here
it means that not out of let's say sexual desire or attraction
but because this was a poor, here she was she was an
abandoned... nobody wanted to marry her and he wanted to, there was
no husband to take her and to be her protector. So he
did it purely for the sake of her and for her benefit
and לשם שמים. LeShem Shamayim. And therefore
it's like he gave birth to her. Now of course I think
for a lot of us that idea of thinking about one's spouse
as if they gave birth to another does not... it strikes a
dissonant chord, but again if you guess... imagine you know this type
of a patriarchal society and actually often sometimes the husband was much
older than the... than the wife. Wife, there was an element of
sort of being the wife's protector and provider and all of that,
so here is this abandoned
girl, nobody's interested in her, so it says it's as if he
gave birth to her. All right.
יריעות Yeriyot now, it also says that and יריעות, Yeriyot, but this
is now being read as not a different wife but a different
name for מרים. Miriam.
So שהיו פניה דומין ליריעות. she'ha'yu paneha domin le'yeriyot. Her face was
like curtains, they were like drawn, you know, it was long, elongated,
pale, that's how she looked because of her illness. ואלו בניה, Ve'eilu
baneha, these are her children. אל תקרי בניה, Al tikri baneha, don't
read בניה, baneha, her children, אלא בוניה, ella boneha, the things that
built her, like you know, אל תקרי בנייך אלא בונייך, al tikri
banayich ela bonayich, so and meaning, and now it's going to describe
how because כלב Kalev married her, then she was she got better
and she was strengthened and she became a healthy woman. ישר, Yashar,
so the first son is ישר, Yashar, שישר את עצמו, she'yishar et
atzmo, that talking about כלב Kalev that he made himself straight, רש"י
Rashi says meaning by going on the straight path and not following
the מרגלים, Meraglim, you could also say he made himself straight in
the context of this מדרש Midrash that he married her when nobody
else would. שובב, Shovav, ששובב את יצרו, she'shovev et yitzro, he subjugated
שובב Shovav is the next name, he subjugated his יצר, yetzer, his
desire, again רש"י Rashi says to not go with the מרגלים, Meraglim,
but you could also say maybe desire to go after some woman
that he was more attracted to.
וארדון, ve'Ardon, שרדה את יצרו, she'rada et yitzro, same idea. ארדון, Ardon,
he he subjugated his יצר. yetzer. Okay, ואיכא דאמרי ve'ika de'amri so
because כלב Kalev married her, it's בניה, baneha, it's very interesting, it
goes both from being like her father and now having it like
her son, he's playing both roles, but בניה baneha being read as
בוניה, boneha, he is the one that gave her standing and protection.
Okay,
ואיכא דאמרי ve'ika de'amri על שפניו דומין לוורד. al she'panev domin le'vered.
It's
that ארדון Ardon is because his face was ruddy as a what
do you call it, as a rose. לאשור אבי תקוע, Le'Ashur avi
Tekoa, now ואשור אבי
תקוע, ve'Ashur avi Tekoa, this person אשור Ashur the father of תקוע,
Tekoa, היו שתי נשים, hayu shtei nashim, had two wives, and we're
going to identify this with כלב Kalev as well, חלאה ונערה. Hel'ah
ve'Na'arah.
Okay, those are his wives. אשור זה כלב, Ashur zeh Kalev, again
we this is כלב, Kalev, ולמה נקרא שמו אשור, ve'lamah nikra shemo
Ashur, why אשור, Ashur, שהושחרו פניו בתעניות. she'hush'cheru panav be'ta'aniyot.
His face grew black with the fasts that he took, the religious
fasting he did to pray to God to help save him from
the מרגלים, Meraglim, which is quite interesting right, because I think we
get a sense when we read you know the פסוקים, psukim, ועבדי
כלב עקב הייתה רוח אחרת עמו, ve'avdi Kalev ekev hayta ruach acheret
imo, that כלב Kalev had this courage and the strength and he
was willing to stand up against the מרגלים Meraglim even in the
presence of all בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael when everybody was gathered against
them against him,
but nevertheless here we see that at least he would not could
not just rely on his own fortitude and courage, he had to
really pray to God to have the strength to withstand the pressure.
Okay, אבי, avi, so what does it mean the father, שנשא לה
כאב, she'nasa lah ke'av, again he became like a father to מרים,
Miriam, that point again. תקוע, Tekoa, שתקע ליבו לאביו שבשמים. she'taka libo
le'aviv she'ba'shamayim. He you know he he planted his heart, he like
you תקע, taka, you're like you know you you like you drive
in a stake to his Father in Heaven. Again presumably for the
מרגלים, Meraglim, but again could also be read in the context of
doing everything לשם שמים l'shem shamayim in terms of marrying מרים. Miriam.
היו שתי נשים, Hayu shtei nashim, he had two
wives, נעשית מרים כשתי נשים. na'asit Miriam k'shtei nashim. So these refer
to מרים. Miriam. מרים Miriam was became like two wives. How is
this? Because it calls her חלאה ונערה. Hel'ah ve'Na'arah. So she went
from being a חלאה, Hel'ah, from being sickly to being like a
נערה, Na'arah, to being like a young woman.
לא חלאה ונערה הוה, Lo Hel'ah ve'Na'arah havah, her name it was
neither a woman by the name of חלאה Hel'ah or נערה, Na'arah,
אלא בתחילה חלאה, ella bitchilah Hel'ah, originally this is describing מרים, Miriam,
she was sickly, ולסוף נערה, u'lesof Na'arah, and then she became as
strong and healthy as a young woman. ובני חלאה, U'vnei Hel'ah, continuing
in the פסוק, pasuk, the children of חלאה, Hel'ah, now meaning מרים,
Miriam, צרת וצחר ואתנן. Tzereth ve'Tzohar ve'Etnan. Okay, so again we're going
to interpret this not literally her children, but describing this story here
and what happened once she got better. So צרת, Tzereth, שנעשית צרה
לחברותיה. she'na'asit tzarah le'chaveroteha. She became a competitor to all of her
friends, meaning other women around, now she became so beautiful that all
the other women were jealous of her. וצחר, ve'Tzohar, שהיו פניה דומין
כצהריים, she'hayu paneha domim ke'tzohorayim, צחר Tzohar her face her her face
was as bright as like the midday. She she had a glow
now that she became healthy. ואתנן, ve'Etnan, which is a gift to
a prostitute, שכל הרואה אותה מוליך אתנן לאשתו. she'kol haro'eh otah molich
etnan le'ishto. Anybody who saw her was filled with so much lust
and desire that they had to go to beg their wives to
have sex with them and the גמרא Gemara says would even offer
them like as well like a payment for a prostitute. So again
a little disturbing image. Okay, וייצא, ve'yatz, that's the end. Anyway that's
how we know that the בתים Batim all that was in- all
that was in service of saying that the בתים Batim was בתי
מלכות Batei Malchus which descended from מרים Miriam because מרים Miriam married
כלב Kalev and we’re saying that דוד Dovid descended from כלב. Kalev.
Okay, back to the story of פרעה. Paroh. ויצו פרעה לכל עמו,
Vayetzav Paroh lechol amo, Paroh commanded his entire nation to say, any
child any son who is born you should throw him into the
Nile. אמר רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא, Amar Rabbi Yose b'rabbi Chanina, אף
על עמו גזר af al amo gazar because it says לכל עמו,
lechol amo, so and it doesn't say any child that's born to
the Hebrews, but any any son that is born, he commanded his
entire people to throw even their own sons that day into the
Nile. Why? Rashi quotes a מדרש תנחומא Midrash Tanchuma because the astrologers
of פרעה Paroh looked in the heaven and said, ah, today the
savior of the Israelites will be born, and we do not know
if he is Egyptian or or a Hebrew slave or a Hebrew,
and the reason obviously for the ambiguity is because משה Moshe was
born you know as a Hebrew, but he grew up in the
house of פרעה, Paroh, he's even identified in the תורה, Torah, איש
מצרי ish mitzri by בנות binos by the daughters of יתרו, Yisro,
so they were unclear about that, but they knew he was born
today, so therefore פרעה Paroh commanded his entire nation, any any boy
that is born throw him into the Nile. Okay.
Okay. אמר רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא, Amar Rabbi Yose b'rabbi Chanina, שלש
גזירות גזר. shalosh gezeros gazar. פרעה Paroh had three three גזירות. gezeros.
בתחילה אם בן הוא והמיתן אותו, bitchila im ben hu v'hamiten oso,
first to the מיילדות, meyaldos, to the midwives, if it's a boy
kill
him. ובסוף u'v'sof and afterwards ואחר כך v'achar kach some switch the
גירסא. girsa. כל הבן הילוד היאורה תשליכהו, kol haben hayilod hayeorah tashlichuhu,
throw every boy into the Nile and here being understood as we'll
see in a second to be Hebrew boys. ולבסוף על עמו גזר
u'l'vasof al amo gazar and then at the end ultimately he even
told his own people to throw their own sons that were born
on that day. Okay, now so that's the edict and now that's
setting the scene for now משה Moshe is about
to be conceived and born with that edict in place of throwing
the boys into the Nile.
וילך איש מבית לוי, Vayelech ish mibeis Levi, so a man went
from the house of Levi, this is עמרם Amram who marries יוכבד.
Yocheved. ולהיכן הלך, u'l'heichan halach, where did he go? What do you
mean he went? Now obviously in the פסוקים pesukim it's sort of
it's a way of giving drama to this new thing. You know,
פרעה Paroh made this edict and then this new thing the then
this you know this important thing happened that עמרם Amram took יוכבד,
Yocheved, you know man took this woman and it doesn't even name
them because it's you know focusing on the birth of משה Moshe
and so on. But anyway the גמרא Gemara wants to say what
is the meaning of the word וילך. vayelech. ולהיכן הלך, u'l'heichan halach,
where did he go? אמר רב יהודה בר זבינא, Amar Rav Yehuda
bar Zvina, שהלך בעצת בתו, shehalach b'atzas bito, he followed the advice
of his daughter. Famous מדרש, Midrash, תנא tana and ties back to
מרים Miriam who we were discussing before. עמרם גדול הדור היה. Amram
gadol hador hayah. עמרם Amram was the great of the generation, you
know the great personage, religious leader of the generation or political leader
or both. כיוון שגזר פרעה הרשע כל הבן הילוד היאורה תשליכהו, keivan
shegazar Paroh harasha kol haben hayilod hayeorah tashlichuhu, once the edict was
to throw every baby boy into the Nile,
so then what did he do? אמר לשווא אנו עמלים, amar l'shav
anu ameilim, he says then it's for naught that we're you know
having this effort, this work,
meaning and having children, they'll just be murdered. It's interesting the phrase
of עמלים, ameilim, effort, because not even referring to the raising of
the children, it's the birthing of the children and you know that
are and then their being cast immediately into the Nile. But so
again it's the word of עמלים ameilim is a little bit strange
here, it's the women who bear the the pregnancy and the birth,
but anyway it's for naught that we are having children. עמד וגירש
את אשתו, amad v'geireish es ishto, what is the point? So he
divorced his wife. Now why did he divorce his wife? Why didn't
he just stop having sex with her? Because as we'll see in
a minute, well first of all one could say that that it
would not be you know the fair to be married and to
be not having have the have the you know sex as a
part of the marriage. But it also seems that it's more because
he wanted to make it as a public statement and he wanted
other people to see what he was doing and how this is
the way he felt that they would sort of resist you know
פרעה's Paroh גזירה. gezeira. So or or at least respond to פרעה's
Paroh גזירה. gezeira. So he he divorced his wife making clear that
he's not going to be having any they're not going to be
having any
children. עמדו כולם וגירשו את נשותיהם, amdu kulam v'geirshu es neshoseihem, so
everybody followed suit. They got up all the men and they divorced
their wives. אמרה לו בתו, amrah lo bito, his daughter said to
him, אבא קשה גזירתך יותר משל פרעה, abba kasha gezeirasecha yoser mishel
Paroh, what you're doing is worse than what Paroh's doing. שפרעה לא
גזר אלא על הזכרים, sheParoh lo gazar ela al hazcharim, Paroh's edict
only applies to the male children. ואתה גזרת על הזכרים ועל הנקיבות,
v'ata gazarta al hazcharim v'al hanekeivos, by not having children that means
even no female children will be born. That's the effect of your
edict, even though it's not an edict it was an act, but
it was an act that was meant to be followed. Okay. פרעה
לא גזר אלא בעולם הזה, Paroh lo gazar ela ba'olam hazeh, Paroh's
edict only applies to this worldly life. ואתה בעולם הזה ובעולם הבא,
v'ata ba'olam hazeh u'v'olam haba, by children not being born it means
that their souls won't get to עולם הבא, Olam Haba, so even
if they were immediately killed they'd at least they would their souls
would have
עולם הבא. Olam Haba. פרעה הרשע ספק מתקיימת גזירתו ספק אינה מתקיימת,
Paroh harasha xafek miskayemes gezeiraso safek einah miskayemes, Paroh, you don't know
if his edict will be filled. foreshadowing that at least by משה
Moshe it wasn't.
So ואתה, ve-atah, but you,
צדיק, tzaddik, בוודאי שגזירתך מתקיימת. be-vadai she-gzeiratecha mitkayemet. But you are a
righteous person, you're not a רשע rasha like פרעה. Paroh. So again
you're the צדיק, tzaddik, he's the רשע, rasha, but what you're doing
is more harmful than what the רשע rasha is doing. Because as
a
צדיק, tzaddik, things that you decree
will stand, will take effect, will be followed. שנאמר ותגזר אומר ויקם
לך. she-ne'emar ve-tigzar omer ve-yakom lach. So and he declares and it
gets established. That is what happens by a צדיק. tzaddik. So what
you're doing is worse than what פרעה Paroh is doing. He's the
רשע, rasha, you're the צדיק, tzaddik, but what you're doing is actually
having a worse effect. Okay, so what did he do? עמד
והחזיר את אשתו. amad ve-hechezir et ishto. He listened to מרים, Miryam,
that's וילך איש, Vayelech ish, and therefore, ויקח את בת לוי, Vayikach
et bat Levi, he remarried his
wife. עמדו
כולם והחזירו את נשיהם, amdu kulam ve-hecheziru et nesheihem, and then they
all followed suit. Okay, so that's how the פסוק pasuk starts, sounds
like it's the first marriage, but really it's a remarriage. You understand
also why חז"ל Chazal had to do this, because אהרן Aharon and
מרים Miryam are older, and it's clear right in the פסוק, pasuk,
ותתצב אחותו מרחוק. va-teitatzeiv achoto me-rachok. So how could it be that
he just had married יוכבד Yocheved and she became pregnant with משה?
Moshe? Obviously they had to have children from beforehand. So they put
this story about divorce and remarriage. And if you think about it,
continuing to have children in the face of that גזירה gezeirah is
the real act of defiance, not sort of divorcing
and ultimately succumbing to the גזירה, gezeirah, making it easier for
פרעה's Paroh wicked deed to be fulfilled. So he followed his daughter's
advice.
ויקח, Vayikach, so he took the daughter of לוי. Levi. ויחזיר מבעי
ליה? Vayachazir mibei lei? It should have said he took her back,
he remarried her. אמר רבי יהודה בר ביזנא, Amar Rabbi Yehuda bar
Bizna, שעשה לה מעשה ליקוחין. she-asah lah ma'aseh likuchin. No, he made
such a big deal about this remarriage that it was like a
first wedding.
הושיבה באפריון, hoshivah b'apiryon, set her on a throne, ואהרן ומרים מרקדין
לפניה, ve-Aharon ve-Miryam merakedin lefaneha, and אהרן Aharon and מרים Miryam were
dancing in front of her. מלאכי השרת אמרו, malachei ha-shareit amru, and
the heavenly angels sang out, 'אם הבנים שמחה', Eim ha-banim semeichah, mother
of children is rejoicing. Is she rejoicing because of her two children
right now, אהרן Aharon and מרים, Miryam, that now she is back
to be married to עמרם? Amram? Is it also suggesting the future
birth of משה? Moshe? That's the אם הבנים שמחה. Eim ha-banim semeichah.
Anyway, this was a whole major wedding and to-do, so also like
a big deal which is leading in, I mean in the context
it's maybe to make a big deal that we are remarrying our
wives, but also now it has this beautiful backdrop and setting leading
into the conceiving and birthing of משה. Moshe. Okay,
בת לוי, bat Levi, he married the daughter of לוי. Levi. אפשר
בת מאה ושלושים שנה הויא וקרי לה בת? efshar bat me'ah u-shloshim
shanah hava'i ve-kari lah bat? Is it possible that you call her
the daughter of לוי? Levi? Now בת bat doesn't mean just that,
you wouldn't say בן ben because it means he's a child, but
anyway, because somehow the גמרא Gemara emphasizes why how can you say
בת bat which implies that she's young? We have a tradition that
she was 130 years old at the time of the birth of
משה. Moshe. So how where's this tradition coming from? דאמר רבי חמא
ברבי חנינא, de-amar Rabbi Chama bar Rabbi Chanina, זו יוכבד שהורתה בדרך
ולידתה בין החומות. zo Yocheved she-horatah ba-derech ve-leidatah bein ha-chomot. זו יוכבד,
zo Yocheved, the פסוק pasuk that he's referring to refers to יוכבד
Yocheved who was
pregnant, her pregnancy
was when they were coming down to מצרים, Mitzrayim, and she was
born the minute that they were entering in. שנאמר, she-ne'emar, as the
verse says, 'אשר ילדה אותה ללוי במצרים', asher yaldah otah le-Levi be-Mitzrayim,
that she gave birth to
her to לוי Levi in מצרים. Mitzrayim. And the midrashic reading of
this
is: לידתה במצרים, leidatah be-Mitzrayim, she was given birth to in מצרים,
Mitzrayim, ואין הורתה במצרים, ve-ein horatah be-Mitzrayim, but she was never,
her pregnancy of her did not take place in מצרים. Mitzrayim. So
how could it be that her mother was pregnant with her out
of מצרים Mitzrayim and not pregnant with her in מצרים, Mitzrayim, and
she was but she was born in מצרים? Mitzrayim? It must be
that she was born at the moment they entered מצרים, Mitzrayim, so
she was born in מצרים, Mitzrayim, but she wasn't, her mother wasn't
pregnant with her in מצרים, Mitzrayim, and that's בין החומות, bein ha-chomot,
between the walls, as they're entering into the walls that
surrounds Egypt, or the capital city, whatever. So that's יוכבד. Yocheved. Now
why did חז"ל Chazal interpret it this way? Because there is a
problem with the פסוקים. psukim. When the פסוקים psukim say, when it
lists the number of people that came down to מצרים, Mitzrayim, if
you count, it's 69, and then it says there were 70 people
who had come down to מצרים. Mitzrayim. So the way it resolves
it is this interpretation which is linked to this פסוק. pasuk. Oh,
she was only pregnant with her when they were coming down, so
there was only 69 when they were coming down, but the moment
they entered מצרים Mitzrayim there were 70. So it resolves that problem
in the פסוקים. psukim. So now, if יוכבד Yocheved was born when
they entered מצרים, Mitzrayim, and they left, they were there for 210
years, that computation we can do another time, and משה Moshe was
80 when they left, so משה Moshe was born when יוכבד Yocheved
was 130. So how could it call her a בת, bat, a
daughter? So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רבי יהודה... amar Rabbi Yehuda...
She restored like by שרה Sarah the signs of youthfulness. She got
her period back if she was going to get pregnant now with
משה, Moshe, so she became like a young woman. I should mention
that the אבן עזרא Ibn Ezra has a strong critique of this.
He says, how could it be with שרה Sarah she was 90,
and the תורה Torah makes such a big deal about the miracle?
And here you're saying it was 130, and how could it just
sort of pass over without mention? רמב"ן Ramban has a whole response,
there are a lot of miracles that happen that the תורה Torah
doesn't mention, hidden miracles and so on. Anyway, that's what we have.
Now, אמר
רב יהודה... Amar Rav Yehuda... oh we just did that. ותהר האשה
ותלד בן. Vatahar ha-isha vateled ben. And now the woman became pregnant
and she gave birth to a son. Now, יוכבד Yocheved being pregnant
with משה, Moshe, והות מעוברה בתלת ירחי מעיקרא. vahavas me-abra bitlat yarchei
mei-ikara.
We're going to see in a second that according to the גמרא,
Gemara, she actually was pregnant three months before עמרם Amram remarried her,
which is fascinating, right? The all this amazing thing, he remarried her,
and they had this wedding party, and this procession, and all of
that, and she became pregnant actually, no. Now her pregnancy was obvious,
but actually she had been pregnant three months before, even before the
וילך איש. Vayelech Ish. So we'll see in a minute why the
גמרא Gemara says that, but now it's assuming that, and it wants
to understand so how do we read the פסוק pasuk that says
she became pregnant if she was already pregnant? So the גמרא Gemara
says, אמר רב יהודה בר זבינא מקיש לידתה להורתה. Amar Rav Yehuda
bar Zvina makish leidosah le-horosah.
The reason to do this is it really just sort of said
she gave birth now to משה. Moshe. Why did it say she
got pregnant and gave birth even though the pregnancy happened earlier? To
connect the idea of the pregnancy to the birth. מה הורתה שלא
בצער אף לידתה שלא בצער, Mah horosah she-lo betza'ar af leidosah she-lo
betza'ar, the same way the pregnancy was without child-bearing pains, she gave
birth without child-bearing pains. Now,
it might mean that the גמרא Gemara here is not referring to
the pregnancy
because ותהר, vatahar, she became pregnant, could really mean in the context
she conceived and she gave birth. So it could mean that the
conception was without pain. As we know, pregnancy is often very much
with difficulties and with pain. But that's the reason that it emphasizes
this to tell you this amazing miracle or fact, מכאן לנשים צדקניות
שלא היו בפתקו של חוה. mikan lenashim tzidkaniyos she-lo hayu befitko shel
Chava. And this tells you that righteous women were not in the
edict against חוה, Chava, that they would give birth in pain. For
righteous women, they are free from that curse. It's actually
interesting when epidurals came out and to give women in childbirth, there
was those from the Catholic Church that were opposed to it because
of the curse of
חוה, Chava, and from the Jewish community there was never an opposition
because curses is not something like we should be doing the curse,
curse is something to be freed from. And here חוה, Chava, this
is not a necessarily an endorsement about epidurals, that's a completely other
discussion. Anyway, okay. Moving on. ותרא
אותו כי טוב הוא. Vatere oso ki tov hu. So she gave
birth to משה Moshe and she saw that he was good. So
what does it mean she saw that he was good? As the
רמב"ן Ramban I think says on the
פסוק, pasuk, every mother thinks that their child is the most beautiful,
adorable child in the world. What special thing here means that she
saw that he was good? So תניא, tanya, רבי מאיר אומר טוב
שמו. Rabbi Meir omer Tov shemo. No, it just means that she
named him טוב. Tov. Although it's funny she saw that he was
good, but okay. The nice thing about this is that now he
has a Hebrew name given by his mother. The name משה, Moshe,
by the way, we often say it means to draw from the
water, that's what רש"י Rashi says, try to find a Hebrew word
that means to draw, but really, משה Moshe is an Egyptian
word. רעמסס, Rameses, for example, Ramsey is Ra-Moshe, son of Ra, born
to Ra. So כי מן המים משיתיהו ki min hamayim meshisihu really
means I birthed him from the water, which is a very powerful
image
there in terms of בת פרעה. Bas Pharaoh. So actually משה Moshe
with a Hebrew name... an Egyptian name, so now actually you have
a Hebrew name given by his mother. The name was טוב. Tov.
רבי יהודה אומר טוביה שמו. Rabbi Yehuda omer Tuvia shemo. His name
was טוביה. Tuvia. I'm not sure where he gets it but כי
טוב הוא, ki tov hu, I guess the הוא... hu... טוב הוא
tov hu and הוא יה, hu Ya, God, טוביה. Tuvia. Okay.
רבי נחמיה אומר הגון לנביאות. Rabbi Nechemia omer Hogun lenevu'ah. She saw
that he somehow, I don't know how, she sensed that this person,
this baby, had the potential for prophecy. That's what it means כי
טוב הוא. ki tov hu. It doesn't tell you how she sensed
that.
אחרים אומרים נולד כשהוא מהול. Acheirim omrim nolad keshehu mahul. Here's now
something she could see. He was born without a foreskin, and that
showed that it was a very special child.
וחכמים אומרים, vachachamim omrim, and the sages say, בשעה שנולד משה נתמלא
הבית כולו אורה. besha'ah shenolad Moshe nitmalei habayis kulo or. When משה
Moshe was born, the whole house filled with light. A very powerful
image, רש"י Rashi quotes this on the תורה, Torah, so probably people
are familiar with it. And that's really like כי טוב. ki tov.
So probably people are familiar with this, and that's really like כי
טוב הוא, ki tov hu, like oh my God, like you understand
that there's something miraculous about this child.
And we're going to make a nice connection from the פסוקים. pesukim.
כתיב הכא ksiv hacha ותרא אותו כי טוב הוא, vatere oso ki
tov hu, she saw him that he was good. וכתיב התם uchsiv
hatam it says by the creation of light, וירא אלהים את האור
כי טוב. vayar Elokim es ha'or ki tov. It's really fascinating when
you look at it. It's almost like exactly ותרא כי טוב הוא,
vatere ki tov hu, וירא את האור כי טוב. vayar et ha'or
ki tov. So this refers to the tremendous, like the divine light
that filled the house. ותצפנהו שלושה ירחים. vatispenehu shlosha yerachim. Now she
hid him for three months.
Now, how did she manage to hide him for three months is
the question of the גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא Gemara somehow is assuming
that, you know, that, that the Egyptians were paying
attention to when this remarriage occurred and were counting nine months from
there. So they should have been out to look for him exactly
at that moment. You know, nine months from the remarriage. How did
she manage to get away with hiding him for three months? So,
and if they had a way to find babies, you know, without
paying attention to who was marrying who and when they imagined the
pregnancy and the conception occurred, they had a way to find babies,
then why didn't they find him earlier? So how do we explain
this ability to hide him for three months? So let's take a
look.
דלא מנו מצריים אלא משעת הדרא, delo manu Mitzrayim ela mish'as hadra,
because they counted nine months, I mean they must have seen that
יוכבד Yocheved was pregnant, but maybe they didn't know how far along.
And they counted, so they saw this woman that she was pregnant
and they figured, oh, how, when are we going to expect her
to give birth? Well, I guess she got pregnant when, when עמרם,
Amram, when we saw that all these Hebrews remarried their wives. So
they were planning on nine months from that date. Once they walked
around and saw, or, you know, it wouldn't be earlier than that,
maybe it'd be later than that, but they saw יוכבד Yocheved pregnant,
they knew we'll start paying attention, you know, nine months from the
date of remarriage.
Okay, and where were we? והיא הויא מעברא בי תלתא ירחי מעיקרא,
vehi hava me'abra bei tlata yarchei me'ikara, but she as we said
earlier, because this was the way to explain how she got away
with it for three months, was actually pregnant three months before the
remarriage. So even though the remarriage was a big deal, it actually
served to buy them three months because the Egyptians counted based on
that. Okay, ולא יכלה עוד הצפינו, velo yachla od hatzpino, she could
no longer hide him. אמאי תצפניה ותיזיל, amai tispneya vesizil, just continue
hiding him. Now we sort of already said because now they're, now
they're going to be looking for him, but the question is how
are they going to find him? What made her, now that they
were focused on trying to find this baby, you know, what was
going to enable them to find him that would not make it
possible for מרים Miriam to continue hiding, for יוכבד Yocheved to continue
hiding? אלא כל היכא דהוה שמעי מצריים דמתילד ינוקא, ela kol heicha
d'hava shamei Mitzrayim demisyalid yanuka, whenever they heard that a child, that
a baby was born, and here they figured out that a baby
was expected to be born, ממטו ינוקא התם, mamtu yanuka hatam, they
would bring an infant to the place where they knew that a
baby was
born, היכא דלישמעיניה ומיעיא, heicha delishmeinih u'mi'aya, in order that they would
like slap the infant on the תוכעס tuches and he would cry,
and that would cause the other baby to cry, and that's how
they would find the hidden babies. So once they knew to start
looking, she knew she could no longer hide him. Now,
okay, so where are we? דכתיב אחזו לנו שועלים שועלים קטנים, dichsiv
achazu lanu shualim shualim ktanim, based on a פסוק pasuk in שיר
השירים Shir Hashirim which is read in the context of the whole,
you know, redemption, small little foxes meaning by using little babies to
find other babies. Okay, ותקח לו תיבת גומא, vatikach lo teivas gome,
she took a basket of reeds, of wicker. מאי שנא גומא, mai
shna gome, why did she pick wicker? אמר רבי אלעזר, amar Rabbi
Elazar, מכאן לצדיקים שממונם חביב עליהם יותר מגופם. mikan l'tzadikim shemamounam chaviv
aleihem yoser migufam. From here we see that righteous people, you know,
they want to be economical in terms of how they, you know,
use their money. So this was a cheap material, and they're very
careful with how they use their money. Why? וכל כך למה לפי
שאין פושטין ידיהם בגזל. vechol kach lama lefi she'ein poshtin yedeihem begazel.
Since they are so careful not to steal or ever take any
money that doesn't belong to them, they're also very economical with how
they use their money. Now this is quite disturbing, I mean besides
that it brings up certain stereotypes, it's also disturbing because really, this
is what you're going to be economical when it comes to creating
a basket that's supposed to save your child? So the גמרא Gemara
immediately suggests another answer.
So, רבי שמואל בר נחמני אמר, Rabbi Shmuel bar Nachmani amar, דבר
רך שיכול לעמוד בפני דבר רך ובפני דבר קשה. davar rach sheyachol
la'amod bifnei davar rach uvifnei davar kasheh. No, they picked wicker because
it was flexible. And if it's flexible, then as it's going down
the Nile, it'll be able to bend whether it encounters something flexible
or something hard. Where if you have something hard, it could puncture
and it actually would not be as good to protect the child.
Okay, ותחמרה בחמר ובזפת, vatachmira vachamer uvazafet, she plastered it with plaster
and pitch, tar. תנא חמר מבפנים וזפת מבחוץ, tana chamer mibifnim vezafet
mibachutz, the plaster was on the inside and the tar was on
the outside of the casket, basket, כדי שלא יריח אותו צדיק ריח
רע, kedei shelo yariach oso tzadik rei'ach ra, so the צדיק, tzadik,
you know, Moshe, this little צדיק, tzadik, should not smell the bad
smell of the tar. That's why the tar was on the outside.
the tar was on the inside, meaning the lower layer, closer to
the wicker, and the plaster was on top of it to protect
the smells that would come from the tar. Okay. ותשימה בה את
הילד vatasem ba es hayeled she put the child into the basket.
ותשם בסוף vatasem basuf and put him into the reeds. רבי אלעזר
אמר ים סוף. Rabbi Elazar amar Yam Suf. It was the Yam
Suf. Of course it doesn't exactly work because we know it's the
היאור, haye'or, so רבי שמואל בר נחמני אמר אגם. Rabbi Shmuel bar
Nachmani amar agam. No, it actually means a swamp, a place where
there are reeds. כדכתיב קנה וסוף kedichsiv kaneh vasof as it says
here, you know, it speaks about reeds. And סוף suf is a
type of a reed.
קמלו Kamalo is his quip. ותרד בת
פרעה לרחוץ על היאור. vatered bas Paroh lirchotz al haye'or. So the
daughter of Pharaoh went to bathe by the Nile. אמר רבי יוחנן
משום רבי שמעון בן יוחאי, Amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi Shimon ben
Yochai, מלמד שירדה לרחוץ מגלולי אביה. melamed sheyarda lirchotz migilulei aviha. It
doesn't just mean bathe, it means to cleanse herself from the excrement,
but here it means the idolatry of her father, and Rashi sort
of using the idea water, how do you cleanse yourself from the
idolatry of your father? It doesn't just mean it means a specific
ritual act, she was going to convert, she was going to use
the Nile to convert. Okay. וכן הוא אומר אם רחץ ה׳ את
צואת בנות ציון vechen hu omer im rachatz Hashem es tzoas benos
Tzion as the פסוק pasuk says, if God has washed clean the
excrement of the daughters of Zion. So you see that washing is
used by referring not just to and that's obviously metaphorical and can
mean the sins. So that's what how washing can serve as that
metaphor. ונערותיה הולכות venaaroseiha holchos and her young women were going, you
know, alongside of her. אמר רבי יוחנן אין הליכה זו אלא לשון
מיתה. Amar Rabbi Yochanan ein halicha zu ela leshon misa. הולכות Holchos
in this context means that they were going to die. וכן הוא
אומר vechen hu omer and it says, הנה אנכי הולך למות hineh
anochi holech lamus here I am going to die. So here it
means going to die, not necessarily what it means by it, but
here it does and as we'll see because of a דרשה drasha
we're about to make. ותרא את התבה בתוך הסוף vatere es hateivah
besoch hasuf she saw the basket in the reeds. כיון דחזו דקבעי
לאצלויי למשה keivan dechazu dekaba'ei l'atzloyei le-Moshe once her maidservants saw that
she was going to save משה, Moshe, אמרו לה amru la they
said to her, גבירתנו מנהגו של עולם מלך בשר ודם גוזר גזירה
gevirtenu minhago shel olam melech basar vadam gozer gezeira
normally in the way of the world even if a king of
flesh and blood, now who would say a king of flesh and
blood unless it was being contrasted to God, and here God is
not going to be mentioned, but okay, if a normal king were
going to make a גזירה, gezeira, אם כל העולם כולו אין מקיימין
אותה בני ביתו מקיימין אותה. im kol ha'olam kulo ein mekayemin osa
benei beiso mekayemin osa. Even in a context where the rest of
the world would not listen to this king's edicts, his family minimally
would listen to his edicts. It's funny, sometimes, you know, the family
gives themselves permission not to follow the rule, but okay, anyway, minimally
his family should follow the edict. So in this case, ואת עוברת
על גזירת אביך ve'at overes al gezeiras avich you're going to come
and violate the edict of your father who said that the babies
should be cast in the river and you're going to be saving
a baby. בא גבריאל וחבטם בקרקע. Ba Gavriel vechavatam bakarka. גבריאל Gavriel
the angel came and banged them into the ground to, you know,
they killed them, made them submerged underground, and that's how and they
died as a result. It's actually, you know, interesting because here the
king making a גזירה, gezeira, פרעה Paroh making a גזירה, gezeira,
evokes the idea of עמרם Amram making a גזירה, gezeira, right? A
צדיק tzadik makes a גזירה gezeira and it gets established. And פרעה
Paroh was said makes a גזירה gezeira and it might, you know,
it might get undermined. Also there מרים Miriam the daughter, right, sort
of undermined her father's גזירה gezeira by persuading him to revoke it,
and here בת פרעה bas Paroh undermined and violated her father's גזירה.
gezeira. So there's very interesting parallels there. Okay. Now.
בא
גבריאל וחבטם. Ba Gavriel vechavatam. ותשלח את אמתה vatishlach es amasa she
sent forth her maidservant, ותקחה vatikacheha and took the basket. רבי יהודה
ורבי נחמיה. Rabbi Yehuda veRabbi Nechemia. דבי רבי יהודה ורבי נחמיה. Debei
Rabbi Yehuda veRabbi Nechemia. חד אמר ידה. chad amar yada.
אמתה amasa means her hand like an אמה, amah, you know, that's
a measurement of the arm. וחד אמר שפחתה. vechad amar shifchasa. אמה
amah also means a maidservant. מאן דאמר ידה Man de'amar yada דכתיב
אמתה. dechisiv amasa.
If you say it means her hand because the word אמה, amah,
that's what it means. It could have said
שפחתה. shifchasa. ומאן דאמר שפחתה Uman de'amar shifchasa דלא כתיב ידה. dilo
kesiv yada. If one wants to say hand, it would have used
a much clearer word for hand, ידה. yada. אמה amah could mean
both, but more by default it means maidservant. So that's why I'm
saying that. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. ולמאן דאמר
שפחתה Ule-man de'amar shifchasa if it means her maidservant, הא אמרת בא
גבריאל וחבטם בקרקע ha amart ba Gavriel vechavatam bakarka didn't you say
that גבריאל Gavriel just, you know, buried them all in the ground?
דשייר לה חדא. Deshayar la chada. No, he left her one maidservant.
דלאו אורחא דבת מלכא למיקם לחודיה. Delav orcha de-bas malka lemeikam lechudeih.
It's not proper for the king's daughter to be alone without any
attendant. So one was left. Okay. ולמאן דאמר ידה Ule-man de'amar yada
now if it means her arm, ולכתוב ידה velichtov yada why did
it use the funny word as אמתה? amasa? Just use the word
ידה yada which is more common.
הא קמשמע לן דאישתרבובי אישתרבובא. Ha kamashma lan de'ishtarbovei ishtarbuba. It means
אמתה, amasa, it means like it went out an אמה amah like
it stretched because אמה amah refers to a sense of distance, right?
So the arm magically stretched, elasticized, and you know, was able to
reach משה. Moshe. דאמר מר וכן אתה מוצא באמתה של בת פרעה.
De'amar mar vechen ata motze be-amasa shel bas Paroh. that with this
is a comment on פרעה Paroh extending the scepter to אסתר, Esther,
you find the same thing by the arm of בת פרעה, Bas
Paroh, וכן אתה מוצא vechen atah motzei that it magically extended, וכן
אתה מוצא בשיני רשעים vechen atah motzei b'shinei resha'im and you find
the same thing by the teeth of the wicked, we just had
blunting the teeth of the בן רשע, ben rasha, דכתיב שיני רשעים
שיברת d'chsiv shinei resha'im shibarta
you have broken the teeth of the wicked, ואמר ריש לקיש v'amar
Reish Lakish אל תקרי שיברת אלא שריבבת al tikrei shibarta ella sherivavta
don't read broken but rather you have actually caused them to elongate,
okay, that's being particularly disfigured. Okay,
okay, so, where were we? ואמר ריש לקיש v'amar Reish Lakish
okay, just a second. ותפתח Vatiftach back, now she opened it up
ותראהו את הילד, vatireihu es hayeled, she saw the child. ותראה מיבעי
ליה, Vatirei miba'lei, it should just say she saw the child, literal
reading of the פסוק pasuk is she saw it or she saw
him comma the child. Why did you need the הוא, hu, she
saw him? Just say she saw the child. אמר רבי יוסי ברבי
חנינא Amar Rabi Yose b'Rabi Chanina שראתה שכינה עמו, sherasa Shechina imo,
she saw the divine presence fitting in very much again with the
sense of the light that filled the house. ותראהו, Vatireihu, she saw
him meaning God את הילד es hayeled with the child. So she
actually saw the divine presence with the child. She saw how you
know how miraculous this child was.
Okay, והנה נער בוכה, vehinei naar bocheh, there was a child crying.
קרי ליה ילד וקרי ליה נער, Kari lei yeled v'kari lei naar,
you called him a ילד yeled which means a baby and called
him a נער naar which usually means a young man. So why
are you calling him a young man? תנא הוא ילד וקולו כנער.
Tanna hu yeled vekolo kenaar. Now obviously he was a baby, but
his voice was like that of a young man, it was a
strong voice. דברי רבי יהודה, Divrei Rabi Yehuda, that's what רבי יהודה
Rabi Yehuda says. אמר לו רבי נחמיה, Amar lo Rabi Nechemia, רבי
נחמיה Rabi Nechemia said back אם כן עשית לו למשה רבינו במום,
im kein asisa lo l'Moshe Rabbeinu bmum, you've turned משה רבינו Moshe
Rabbeinu into a person with a blemish, because for a baby to
have that deep of a voice, that's
that's unusual, that's not
and it's not proper for that to be the voice of a
baby. That would be like a blemish. And as רש"י Rashi adds
also you know a little bit anachronistically in the end the לויים
Leviim were the singers in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, so that
would actually invalidate somebody that had a voice that was you know
that deep already as a child. Okay. אלא מלמד שעשתה לו אמו
חופת נעורים. Ella melamed she'asta lo imo chuppas ne'urim. The word נער
naar means that his mother made a little חופה, chuppah, a little
baby חופה chuppah for him because
because she said you know and put in the basket בתיבה אמרה
שמא לא אזכה לחופתו, bateiva amra shema lo ezkeh l'chuppaso, maybe I
will never see him in his when he gets married, which she
didn't because he got married in מדין. Midian. But okay, but you
know I won't be able to he won't grow up and get
married, I'll make him a little pretend חופה chuppah right now. Also
evokes the חופה chuppah that his mother had on the second taking
on her second marriage. Okay, where were we?
נעורים בתיבה שמא לא אזכה לחופתו. ne'urim bateiva shema lo ezkeh l'chuppaso.
ותחמול עליו, Vatachmol alav, she had compassion on him, בת פרעה. Bas
Paroh. ותאמר מילדי העברים זה, Vatomer miyaldei ha'ivrim zeh, this is one
of the Hebrew children. מנא ידעה? Minai yada? How did she know?
Now obviously context would have been a big hint, but okay, אמר
רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא amar Rabi Yose b'Rabi Chanina שראתה אותו מהול,
sherasa oso mahul, she saw that he was circumcised. This presumably is
not the same point before that he was born without a foreskin,
because that's just a natural occurrence. Must mean that actually he was
circumcised, right, they circumcised him. Okay, זה. zeh. So this this one
is of the Hebrews. So what's the word זה? zeh? אמר רבי
יוחנן מלמד שנתנבאה שלא מדעתה, Amar Rabi Yochanan melamed shenisnabesa shelo mida'atah,
that she prophesied without realizing what she was saying. זה נופל, Zeh
nofel, this one was cast in the Nile ואין אחר נופל, v'ein
acher nofel, but no other baby was cast in the Nile. As
soon as משה Moshe was cast in the Nile the edict stopped
because the edict was in order because the astrologers saw that that
the savior would be born and he would be judged by water.
When this happened the sign in the heavens stopped and therefore the
edict stopped. And what's being said is משה Moshe was also the
only first one of the edict because if you remember before it
says that the edict was given to the entire nation. So there
are different versions here because this makes it sound like before we
had different stages, first to all only all the Hebrews and then
at a later point to the entire nation. This sounds like that
edict of פרעה Paroh was one day to the entire nation. That
was the only time it was said cast the babies in the
Nile and the only baby this happened to was משה, Moshe, nobody
else. Nobody before him, nobody after him.
Okay, which then makes one wonder why you had to have all
that problem about the three months
if the edict didn't come until the day they imagined משה Moshe
was born. So these these things don't exactly work together, but okay.
So only משה. Moshe. והיינו דאמר רבי אלעזר Vehainu d'amar Rabi Elazar
מאי דכתיב mai d'chsiv וכי יאמרו אליכם דרשו אל האובות ואל הידעונים,
v'chi yomru aleichem dirshu el ha'ovos v'el hayidonim,
when they say to you go and seek out the you know
the the people that like raise the dead and they you know
do this sort of necromancy, המצפצפים והמהגים, hamitzpitzpim vehamihagim,
that chirp and that like utter and babble. So this is making
fun of people that sort of these who foretell the future this
פסוק pasuk in
ישעיהו. Yeshayahu. צופים Tzofim and now it's interpreting it in general about
you know astrologers and so on, it's not like it's total nonsense.
צופים Tzofim מצפצפים mitzpitzpim they're reading they see something ואינם יודעים מה
צופים v'einam yodim ma tzofim but they don't know exactly what they
see. מהגים Mahagim they they speak ואינם יודעים מה מהגים v'einam yodim
ma mahagim but they're not. Don't know exactly what they're saying. ראו,
Ra'u, so what do they see? ראו שמושיען של ישראל במים הוא
לוקה. Ra'u shemoshi'an shel Yisrael bamayim hu loke. They saw that the
savior would be punished by water. Before we said they chose water
because they said God would punish measure for measure and wouldn't destroy
the world with water. But okay, here they actually saw a sign
in the heaven that Moshe would be punished with water. עמדו וגזרו
כל הבן הילוד היאורה תשליכוהו. Amdu vegazru kol haben hayilod haye'orah tashlichuhu.
They said, cast every child, and remember even Egyptian children, cast them
into the Nile. כיון דשדיוהו למשה, Keivan deshadyuhu le-Moshe, then that Moshe
was the very first baby that this was done to. As soon
as Moshe was thrown in, again doesn't exactly work. Why was she
hiding him for three months if the גזרה gezerah wasn't around yet?
And when no babies born in those interim three months? But okay,
anyway, Moshe was the first baby this was done to. אמרו תו
לא חזינא כי האי סימנא. Amru tu lo chazina ki hai simana.
We do no longer see that
sign. בטלו לגזרתייהו. Batlu legezerataihu. So then they annulled the edict because
now they said oh, that savior has been cast in the Nile
and has been judged and is dead and we don't have to
worry anymore. So, והם אינם יודעים. Vehem einam yodim. Now what they
didn't understand was כי על מי מריבה הוא לוקה. Ki al Mei
Merivah hu loke. He's not going to be, the savior will be
punished by the waters of Merivah and not by the Nile. And
the fact that they didn't see the sign was because right now
in the Nile he was, you know, no longer, he was in
a pace of danger and if nothing had happened he would have
died, but that was not a permanent sense that he was, that
the savior had been killed.
Okay, והיינו דאמר רבי חמא ברבי חנינא, Vehainu de'amar Rabbi Chama berabi
Chanina, מאי דכתיב, mai dechetiv, what's meant המה מי מריבה, Hemah Mei
Merivah, these are the waters of Merivah אשר רבו asher ravu that
you know,
that were you know, fought, contentious. המה שראו אצטגניני פרעה, Hemah sherau
itztagninei Pharoh, these are the same waters that the astrologers of Pharoh
saw וטעו, Vetau, but you know, oh, they were confused. They thought
it was the Nile. No, no, no, they meant these were the
waters that they were really seeing. Okay, והיינו דקאמר משה, Vehainu deka'amar
Moshe, and that's what Moshe says שש מאות אלף רגלי, Shesh me'ot
elef ragli, six hundred thousand you know people you know is this
people like of like you know infantrymen like the word רגל, regel,
but here רגלי ragli is being read as on account of me.
You know, so רגלי אמר להו משה לישראל, Ragli amar lehu Moshe
le-Yisrael, בשבילי נצלתם כולכם. bishvili nitzaltem kulchem. All six hundred thousand of
you, that's because of me, because when I was cast in the
Nile the edict, the edict ceased. So you all have to thank
me for being saved. Now תוספות Tosafot says wait a minute, the
whole edict was made because of Moshe. So why is he taking
credit for saving them if the whole edict was made because of
him? But he says okay, but once this happened even the whole
desire to kill them which had preceded this, which was to the
midwives even before these astrological signs, all of that stopped and therefore
Moshe, you know, that's why then the edict stopped. Okay,
and we will stop here for today and pick up here tomorrow.